Finding Aid for Sebastian Spering Kresge papers, 1923-1966 [microform]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sebastian Spering Kresge papers (microfilm) 1923-1966
Kresge, Sebastian Spering, 1867-1966.
8 microfilms 7 linear feet
9565 Aa 2
Founder of the S.S. Kresge Company. Business and personal files relating to his financial dealings and to his involvement with various churches and educational institutions; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Kresge papers came to the library in 1983 and 1985 as the gift of Stanley S. Kresge (Donor No. 6888 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The originals of Sebastian Spering Kresge papers are held by the Bentley Historical Library.
Sebastian S. Kresge, founder of the S.S. Kresge Company with more than 850 retail outlets in North America by the end of his life, was born in 1867 at Bald Mount, Pennsylvania.
The son of Pennsylvania Dutch farmers, he attended rural schools and later - by teaching school, working for a grocer, and working on his father's farm - the Fairview Academy and Polytechnic Institute. With earnings from his bee-keeping enterprise, he later attended and graduated from Eastman's Business College at Poughkeepsie, New York, in 1889.
After graduation, Kresge worked as a bookkeeper for three years and a traveling salesman for five years. Not only was he successful in his travels selling hardware and tinware (he saved more than $8000 during those years), but he also became well acquainted with the leading entrepreneurs in the field of five and ten cent retail stores, including Frank W. Woolworth, S.H. Kress, J.J. Newberry and W.T. Grant. He was impressed with the industry, and in 1897 approached one of his customers about forming a partnership. John G. McCrory, who owned several five and ten cent stores, agreed to the deal, and Kresge spent several months learning the business first-hand from the manager of McCrory's Jamestown, New York, store, G.C. Murphy. Shortly thereafter, McCrory and Kresge opened two additional stores, one in Memphis, Tennessee, which was managed by Kresge, and the other in Detroit, Michigan, managed by Murphy for McCrory. When Murphy decided to branch off on his own in 1899, Kresge assumed control of the Detroit store and later that year traded his half interest in the Memphis store to McCrory for complete ownership of the Detroit outlet. A year later, Kresge and his brother-in-law, Charles J. Wilson, formed the firm of Kresge and Wilson and opened a second store in Port Huron, Michigan. By 1907, when Kresge bought out his partner and changed the name of the firm to S.S. Kresge, there was a total of eight stores located in Michigan, Ohio, Indiana, Illinois and Pennsylvania.
Over the next five years, Kresge expanded his chain to 85 stores by buying out smaller chains or opening new outlets, and in 1912 incorporated the business in Delaware as the S.S. Kresge Company. Four years later, with 150 stores, the company was reincorporated in Michigan. Kresge remained president of the firm until 1925, and thereafter served as Chairman of the Board until his death. The company continued its phenomenal growth and expanded into Canada (the S.S. Kresge Company, Ltd., in 1929) and Puerto Rico.
In addition to his business involvement with S.S. Kresge Company, Kresge was the sole owner of Kresge Department Store in Newark, New Jersey, which he established in 1923. He became involved in the field of the full-range department stores when he served as president of Kresge Department Stores, Inc., which owned the Palais Royal department store in Washington, D.C., and controlling interest in The Fair from 1925-1957. In 1920, Mount Clemens (Michigan) Pottery Company was acquired and, as a subsidiary of S.S. Kresge Company, made the dinnerware that was sold in Kresge stores.
Throughout his life, Kresge was concerned with improving the lot of his fellow man and in 1924 established the Kresge Foundation with an endowment of $2 million. Over the next thirty-five years he gave an additional $60 million to the Foundation, which provided assistance to religious, medical, educational, and youth organizations and institutions. As trustee and treasurer, Kresge devoted a good deal of his time to Foundation work.
In addition to his Foundation work, Kresge was a supporter of the prohibition movement. He donated many funds to church organizations (he was a Methodist). Furthermore, he was a member of the Republican party.
Sebastian Kresge was thrice married: in 1897 to Anna E. Harvey, by whom he had five children: Stanley Sebastian, Ruth Harvey, Howard Carrington, Catherine Harriet, and Ann Elizabeth; in 1924 to Doris (Mercer) Harden, and in 1928 to Clara Katherine (Zitz) Swaine. He died at the age of 99 in East Stroudsberg, Pennsylvania, in 1966. Clara survived him.
The Sebastian S. Kresge Papers are divided into two series: Business Records, and Personal Records. The papers were microfilmed in 1994 and are available for inter-library loan. The collection was filmed in its entirety except for a few folders of financial data, such as stock and business receipts.
Subjects:
Kresge, Sebastian Spering, 1867-1966.; Business records.; Kresge Foundation.; Philanthropists--Michigan.; Retail trade.; S.S. Kresge Company.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bronson Methodist Hospital (Kalamazoo, Mich); Buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Business enterprises.; Chelsea (Mich.)--Rest homes.; Chelsea Methodist Home.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings.; Hospitals--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Kalamazoo (Mich.)--Hospitals.; Kresge, Sebastian Spering, 1867-1966.; Kresge family.; Offices--1921-1930.; Rest homes--Michigan--Chelsea.; S.S. Kresge Company.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Business Records
  The Business Records (1937-1966) series is comprised of two subseries, the Chronological Files and the Topical Files, and pertains to Mr. Kresge's tenure as chairman of the board of S.S. Kresge Company, and his involvement with Kresge Department Store, Newark, New Jersey, and Kresge Department Stores Incorporated. The series consists almost entirely of the records of Kresge's nephew and personal secretary, Amos F. Gregory. When Gregory wrote to Kresge, he sent along a carbon copy of each letter so that Kresge could make notes on the copy and return it to him. Incoming correspondence to Gregory includes letters from Kresge and his wife Clara.
  - Chronological Files
    The Chronological Files subseries (5.5 linear feet) is arranged by year, and within each year by topic. Financial records and correspondence, the majority of which concern loans and securities transactions, predominate in these files. Matters pertaining to real estate, investments, incorporations, and capitalizations are also documented, and there are scattered materials related to the Kresge Foundation. (For specific locations of these types of materials, see the line entries in the contents list.) Of particular interest are the 1937 S.S. Kresge Company, C.B. Tuttle files which contain enlightening materials on the attempts by Kresge to keep the price of the company's stock at $26 during the early years of the depression. In addition, the Howard Baldwin files from the 1950s contain correspondence from Baldwin to Kresge regarding a wide variety of important business concerns of The Fair, Kresge-Newark, and the Kresge Foundation. The researcher should also note the Kresge Correspondence files which contain letters to and from Kresge and Gregory. Much of their content concerns financial matters, and on occasion the researcher will find Kresge reflecting on other topics, including politics, causes in which he was interested, and his home life.
    - 1937
      - Baker Land Company: Stockholders Reports, and correspondence concerning company land sales, dividends, and dividend related taxes 1936-1939 (Reel 1)
      - Baldwin, Howard (Reel 1)
        (mostly routine correspondence, but includes interesting 1935 letter explaining mechanics of securing a $2 million loan for S.S. Kresge Company)
      - Banker's Trust Company: materials related to loans; includes 1935, 1936 correspondence (Reel 1)
      - Chambers of Commerce: re: Kresge's memberships, includes 1936 materials (Reel 1)
      - Chase National Bank (mostly regarding loans) 1936-1937 (Reel 1)
      - Fair, The (quarterly and annual stockholders reports and correspondence with President D.F. Kelly) 1935-1937 (Reel 1)
      - Fidelity Union Trust Company (re: loans and Kresge Foundation contribution to the Association to Provide and Maintain a Home for the Friendless) (Reel 1)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.
        - Correspondence 1927-1937 (Reel 1)
        - Real Estate (re: Miami Beach properties, including assessed values, construction permits and plat, and correspondence on taxes) (Reel 1)
        - Refusals (of invitations and requests) 1934-1938 (Reel 1)
      - Kresge Company, S.S. General (1936 annual report) (Reel 1)
      - Tuttle, C.B., Treasurer (re: dividends, loans, and certificates of indebtedness, stock information, one letter from 1938) (Reel 1)
      - Richmond, Virginia (re: rent payments, lease from 1917) (Reel 1)
      - Securities and Exchange Commission (reports and correspondence) 1934-1938 (Reel 1)
      - Slatington, Pennsylvania (re: occupancy by Kresge's relatives, real estate parcels) 1931-1937 (Reel 1)
      - Thomson & McKinnon, Brokers (buy and sell confirmations, account summary reports, correspondence) (Reel 1)
      - Van Deusen, C.B. (brief notes to/from Gregory) 1932-1936 (Reel 1)
    - 1938
      - Baldwin, Howard (re: financial transactions, services rendered, etc.) (Reel 1)
      - Banker's Trust Company (re: loans) (Reel 1)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.
        - Correspondence, 2 folders (Reel 1)
        - 5625 Pine Tree Drive (appraisal, maintenance records, rental and sale 1937-1940) (Reel 2)
        - Real Estate (assessment and taxes for Miami Beach property 1923 sale of Detroit property) (Reel 2)
      - Kresge Company, S.S. (dividend statement, pamphlet) (Reel 2)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: bills, stock, incorporation matters) (Reel 2)
      - Richmond, Virginia (rental matters) (Reel 2)
    - 1939
      - Goodenough, Voorhies, Long & Ryan (re: legal matters) (Reel 2)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 2)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: loans, property taxes, net worth balance sheet) (Reel 2)
      - Price, Waterhouse & Co. (re: loans, profits, journal entries, services rendered) (Reel 2)
      - Springfield, Massachusetts (rental/real estate transactions) 1935-1939 (Reel 2)
      - Steiger, Albert (re: Springfield, Mass.) 1935-1939 (Reel 2)
    - 1940
      - Fair, The (stock information, incorporation materials, information about a damaged garage) (Reel 2)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 2)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: loans to store from Kresge, Federal Unemployment Tax filings) (Reel 2)
    - 1941
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.
        - Correspondence (Reel 2)
        - Real Estate (sale of property, taxes) 1939-1942 (Reel 2)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: interest on loans, rent, social security taxes) (Reel 2)
      - Voorhies, Long, Ryan and McNair (service statements) (Reel 2)
      - Fair, The (annual report, stock purchases and transfers) (Reel 2)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 2)
    - 1942
      - Fair, The (annual report, stock purchases and transfers) (Reel 2)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 2)
      - Kresge Company, S.S. (stockholders meeting announcement) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: interest on loans, sale of property, dividends) (Reel 3)
    - 1943
      - Baker Land Company (stockholders report, sale of stock) (Reel 3)
      - Fair, The (re: stock, proposal for recapitalization) (Reel 3)
      - Fidelity Union Trust Company (money transfer receipt) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: loans, profits and losses, property sales, stock transfers, sale of Steinbach Kresge Company stock) (Reel 3)
        (see also Steinbach Kresge Company)
      - Steinbach Kresge Company (Reel 3)
        (see Kresge Department Store, Newark)
    - 1944
      - Fair, The (purchases and exchanges of stock) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.
        - Correspondence (Reel 3)
        - Real Estate (re: contested real estate commission in connection with Miami Beach property sale) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Department Stores, Inc. (includes Kresge Department Store, Newark; loans, profits, lease renewal, social security taxes; the Steinbach Company; stock) (Reel 3)
      - Voorhies, Long, Ryan and McNair (re: The Fair capitalization and stock transfer; reincorporation of Kresge, Newark; the Kresge Foundation; and dissolution of Kresge Department Stores Inc. 1944-1945) (Reel 3)
    - 1945
      - Bankers Trust Company (re: loans) (Reel 3)
      - Chase National Bank (re: loans) (Reel 3)
      - Fair, The (re: dividends, stock) (Reel 3)
      - First Stroudsburg National Bank (re: deposits and tax receipts) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: loans, employee compensation, taxes, war bonds, and the Steinbach Company) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Department Stores, Inc. (correspondence) (Reel 3)
      - Steinbach Company (re: final payment to Kresge) (Reel 3)
    - 1946
      - Dividends (G.C. Murphy Company dividend notice) (Reel 3)
      - Fair, The (stock) (Reel 3)
      - Guaranty Trust Company (redemption of Fair preferred stock) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Company, S.S. (stockholders meeting announcement) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Department Store, Newark (re: loans, Fair stock, financial audits) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge Department Stores, Inc. (re: stock, annual report) (Reel 3)
      - Voorhies, Long, Ryan and McNair (re: Kresge Foundation, Liquidation of Kresge's holdings of Kresge Department Stores, Inc., stock) (Reel 3)
    - 1947
      - Dividends (notices from G.C. Murphy Company, The Fair, Montgomery Ward) (Reel 3)
      - Fair, The (re: stock) (Reel 3)
      - Gimbel Brothers, Inc. (re: stock, a four-for-three split) (Reel 3)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 4)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (formerly Kresge Department Store, Newark; re: The Fair stock, agreement re: corporate changes to facilitate the issuance of common and preferred stock 1946-1947) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge Department Stores, Inc. (re: stock) (Reel 4)
      - Savings Bonds (applications for) (Reel 4)
    - 1948
      - Attorney's Fee Statement (for rewriting will and other services) (Reel 4)
      - Chase National Bank (re: dividend check) (Reel 4)
      - Fair, The (re: Kresge Foundation holdings of stock December 27, 1948 market transaction of stock) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 4)
      - Kresge Company, S.S. (misc.) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge Department Stores, Inc. (re: dissolution and liquidation) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (re: The Fair stock) (Reel 4)
    - 1949
      - Contributions (to Red Cross and Community Chest 1945-1949) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge Foundation (re: gifts) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 4)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (re: The Fair stock, liquidation of Kresge Department Stores, Inc., etc.) (Reel 4)
    - 1950
      - Baldwin, Howard C. (correspondence) 1950-1951 (Reel 4)
      - Howlett, Thomas F.J. (re: Kresge loan to Howlett) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 4)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc,. (correspondence) (Reel 4)
    - 1951
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.
        - Correspondence (Reel 4)
        - Investments (Reel 4)
      - Kresge Company, S.S. (annual report) (Reel 4)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (re: loans from Kresge to pay for spring and summer merchandise, etc.) (Reel 4)
    - 1952
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 4)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (re: loans from Kresge) (Reel 4)
      - Social Security (Kresge's benefits) (Reel 5)
    - 1953
      - Baldwin, Howard (correspondence) (Reel 5)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 5)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (loans, pension payroll) (Reel 5)
    - 1954
      - Dividends (notices from various companies, request from Kresge for copies of annual reports) (Reel 5)
      - Kresge, Clara K.: Correspondence (requesting Gregory to assist a relative) (Reel 5)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 5)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (re: loans, correspondence) (Reel 5)
      - Voorhies, Long, Ryan and McNair (services rendered) (Reel 5)
    - 1955
      - Babson, Roger W. 1954-1955 (Reel 5)
      - Baldwin, Howard C. (Reel 5)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence
        - General (Reel 5)
        - While in Hospital (Reel 5)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (loans, correspondence) (Reel 5)
    - 1956
      - Baldwin, Howard C. (correspondence) (Reel 5)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 5)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (loans) (Reel 5)
    - 1957
      - Baldwin, Howard C. (correspondence) (Reel 5)
      - Hansen, J.P. ("The Fair", Chicago). 1955-1957 (Reel 5)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - 1958
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - 1959
      - Baldwin, Howard C. (correspondence) (Reel 6)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - 1960
      - Baldwin, Howard C. (correspondence) (Reel 6)
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (correspondence) (Reel 6)
    - 1961
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (Correspondence) (Reel 6)
    - 1962
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (birthday letters) (Reel 6)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (correspondence, letters from Howard Baldwin) (Reel 6)
    - 1963
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
      - Kresge Foundation (list of unpaid grants, grants authorized, grants paid) (Reel 6)
      - Kresge-Newark, Inc. (correspondence, list of rental property incomes) (Reel 6)
    - 1964
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - 1965
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence (Reel 6)
    - 1966
      - Kresge, Sebastian S.: Correspondence
        - General (Reel 6)
        - Retirement (Reel 7)
      - Kresge Company, S.S. (re: stock) (Reel 7)
      - Securities and Exchange Commission (report) (Reel 7)
  - Topical Files
    The Topical Files subseries (one-half linear foot) is also primarily concerned with financial matters. In the Biographical folders, the researcher will find a number of interesting biographical sketches of Kresge which focus on his business career. There are fairly extensive records documenting his stock (Kresge and non-Kresge companies) and bond holdings during given periods of his life.
    - Biographical (re: Kresge's business career)
      - General, 3 folders (Reel 7)
      - Kresge, Doris Mercer (divorce file) (Reel 7)
    - Personal (The Fair, Kresge Department Stores, Inc., Annual Reports 1932-1933 S.S. Kresge Statement of Assets and Liabilities, 1932-1933) (Reel 7)
    - Portrait (1927-1928 correspondence re: portrait of Kresge by Marris & Ewing of Washington D.C.) (Reel 7)
- Personal Records
  The Personal Records series (1948-1959; one linear foot) is also divided into two subseries: Correspondence and Topical Files.
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence subseries is comprised of letters to relatives and friends and responses to various invitations and requests; the content primarily reflects upon Kresge's home life. There is quite a bit of overlap between the business and personal correspondence.
    - 1st Subseries, A-Z (largely 1955-1957)
      - A-C 1956-1957 (Reel 7)
      - D-E 1957, F 1956-1957 (Reel 7)
      - First Miami Beach Methodist Church (Reel 7)
      - Foundation, The First 30 Years 1954-1956 (Reel 7)
      - G-H 1956-1957 (Reel 7)
      - Howell, Mary 1956-1957 (Reel 7)
      - I-J 1955-1956, K 1953-1957, L 1955 (Reel 7)
      - M-O 1957 (Reel 7)
      - P-Q 1955-1957, R 1957 (Reel 7)
      - S 1956-1957, T 1952-1957 (Reel 7)
      - U-W 1957, X-Z 1948-1957 (Reel 7)
  - Correspondence
    The Topical Files subseries relates to Kresge's activities with industry, educational institutions, and various churches. There is one scrapbook with newspaper articles concerning gifts given by the Kresge Foundation. In addition, there are clippings (primarily from the 1950s), and photographs. The photographs pertain to both business and personal aspects of Kresge's life.
    - 2nd Subseries, A-Z
      - [A never received] (Reel 8)
      - B 1952-1958, C 1955-1958 (Reel 8)
      - D-F 1958, G 1957-1958 (Reel 8)
      - H 1956-1958, I-J 1956-1957 (Reel 8)
      - K 1957-1958, L 1956-1958 (Reel 8)
      - M 1956-1959, N-O 1958, P-Q 1957-1958 (Reel 8)
      - R-S 1958, T 1957-1958 (Reel 8)
      - U-V 1957-1958, W 1958, X-Z 1957-1958 (Reel 8)
  - Topical Files
    - Estate of Sebastian S. Kresge (Reel 8)
    - Citations and Certificates (Reel 8)
    - Scrapbook (Reel 8)
    - Clippings, 4 folders (Reel 8)
    - Photographs (includes Stanley Kresge)
      - Personal
        - Awards and Honors (Reel 8)
        - Dedications and Corner Stone Layings (Reel 8)
        - Friends (Reel 8)
        - Home: Miami Beach, Florida (Reel 8)
        - Portraits: Formal and Informal
          - Kresge, Sebastian S., 2 folders (Reel 8)
          - Kresge, Sebastian S. and Clara (Reel 8)
      - Buildings (Bronson Methodist Hospital, Kalamazoo, Michigan; Spear Building, Springfield, Massachusetts; YMCA in Detroit) (Reel 8)
      - Business
        - Kresge-Wilson Store, Toledo, Ohio circa 1906 (Reel 8)
        - London, Ontario Store (Reel 8)
        - Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania, Store Opening (Reel 8)
      - Kresge Foundation: Methodist Home, Chelsea, Michigan (Reel 8)
      - Miscellaneous: includes photo of Kresge with Calvin Coolidge and others, photo of Stanley Kresge (Reel 8)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library also has on deposit S.S. Kresge Company Corporate Records and the Stanley Sebastian Kresge Papers. These records are an important supplement to the Sebastian S. Kresge Papers.